<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lost lover, or, The jealous husband a comedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal by His Majesty's servants / written by Mrs. Manley.</title>
            <author>Manley, Mrs. (Mary de la Rivière), 1663-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51771</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11967475</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11967475</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 36:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lost lover, or, The jealous husband a comedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal by His Majesty's servants / written by Mrs. Manley.</title>
                  <author>Manley, Mrs. (Mary de la Rivière), 1663-1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bently ... F. Saunders ... J. Knapton, and R. Wellington ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOST LOVER; OR, THE <hi>Iealous Husband.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:2"/>
            <p>THE LOST LOVER; OR, THE <hi>Iealous Husband:</hi> A COMEDY.</p>
            <p>As it is Acted at the <hi>THEATRE ROYAL</hi> BY His MAJESTY's
Servants.</p>
            <p>Written by Mrs. <hi>Manley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bently,</hi> in
<hi>Covent-Garden; F. Saunders,</hi> in the <hi>New-Exchange; J. Knapton,</hi>
and <hi>R. Wellington,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THis Comedy by the little ſucceſs it met with in the Acting,
has not at all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived my Expectations; I had ever ſo great a Diſtruſt,
and ſo impartial an Opinion, that nothing but the flattery of my Friends (and
them, one wou'd imagine, Men of too much Senſe to be ſo grosſly
miſtaken, and without whoſe perſwaſion I never deſigned pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
of it) cou'd in the leaſt have held me in ſuſpence of its good or evil
Fortune: and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my Faults, I own it an unpardonable one, to
expoſe, after two years reflection, the Follies of ſeven days, (for barely
in that time this Play was wrought) and my ſelf ſo great a Stranger to the
Stage, that I had lived buried in the Countrey, and in the ſix foregoing
years, had actually been but twice at the Houſe. The better half was 
<pb facs="tcp:51767:4"/>cut; They ſay, 'thas ſuffered by it, tho' they told me, 'twas
poſſible to have too much of a good thing, but I think never too little of
an ill.</p>
            <p>That knowledge I had of the Town was the gentile part, which does
not always afford Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Characters; My deſign in Writing was only to
paſs ſome tedious Country hours, not imagining I ſhould be ſo
ſeverely repay'd. I now know my Faults, and will promiſe to mend them by
the ſureſt way, not attempting to repeat them.</p>
            <p>I am now convinc'd Writing for the Stage is no way proper for a
Woman, to whom all Advantages but meer Nature, are refuſed; If we happen to
have a Genius to Poetry, it preſently ſhoots to a fond deſire of
Imitation. Tho' to be lamely ridiculous, mine was indulged by my Flatterers,
who ſaid, nothing cou'd come from me unentertaining: like a Hero not
contented with Applauſe from leſſer Conqueſts, I find my ſelf not
only diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of my hopes of greater, but even to have loſt all the
glory of the former; Had I confin'd my Senſe, as before, to ſome ſhort
Song of <hi>Phillis,</hi> a Tender Billet, and the freedom of agreeable
Converſation, I had ſtill preſerved the Character of a Witty Woman.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:4"/>
            <p>Give me leave to thank the Well-natur'd Town for Damning me ſo
ſuddenly; They would not ſuffer me to linger in ſuſpence, nor allow me
any degrees of Mortification; neither my Sex, Dreſs, Muſick and Dancing,
cou'd allow it a three Days Reprieve, nor the Modeſty of the Play it ſelf,
prevail with the Ladies to Eſpouſe it: Here I ſhould moſt juſtly
reproach my ſelf, if I did not make all due Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for Sir
<hi>Thomas Skipwith</hi>'s Civility, his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Generoſity, and Gallantry of
Temper, took care nothing on his part ſhou'd be wanting to make it
pleaſing.</p>
            <p>Once more, my Offended Judges, I am to appear before you, once
more in poſſibility of giving you the like Damning Satisfaction; there is a
Tragedy of mine Rehearſing, which 'tis too late to recall, I conſent it
meet with the ſame Fortune: 'Twill for ever rid me of a Vanity too Natural to
our Sex, and make me ſay with a Grecian Hero, <hi>I had been loſt, if I had
not been loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They Object the Verſes wrote by me before <hi>Agnes de
Caſtro,</hi> where, with Poetick Vanity I ſeemed to think my ſelf a
Champion for our Sex; ſome of my Witty Critticks make a Jeſt of my proving
ſo favourable an Enemy, but let me tell them, this was not deſign'd a
Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of that Challenge, being writ two years <pb facs="tcp:51767:5"/>before, and
cannot have a ſmaller Share in their Eſteem than mine: After all, I think
my Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment much ſeverer than I deſerved; I am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the bare Name
of being a Woman's Play damn'd it beyond its own want of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: I will
conclude with <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">That <hi>Plato</hi> and Philoſophy have
taught me to bear ſo great a Loſs (even of Fame) with Patience.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:5"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE,</head>
            <byline>Spoken by Mr. <hi>Horden.</hi>
            </byline>
            <lg>
               <l>THe firſt Adventurer for her fame I ſtand,</l>
               <l>The Curtain's drawn now by a Lady's Hand,</l>
               <l>The very Name you'l cry boads Impotence,</l>
               <l>To Fringe and Tea they ſhou'd confine their Sence,</l>
               <l>And not outſtrip the bounds of Providence.</l>
               <l>I hope then Criticks, ſince the Caſe is ſo,</l>
               <l>You'l ſcorn to Arm againſt a Worthleſs Foe,</l>
               <l>But curb your ſpleen and gall, and trial make,</l>
               <l>How our fair Warriour gives her firſt Attack.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now all ye chattering Inſects ſtraight be dumb,</l>
               <l>The Men of Wit and Senſe are hither come,</l>
               <l>Ask not this Mask to Sup, nor that to ſhow</l>
               <l>Some Face more ugly than a Fifty Beau,</l>
               <l>Who, if our Play ſucceeds, will ſurely ſay,</l>
               <l>Some private Lover helpt her on her way,</l>
               <l>As Female Wit were barren like the Moon,</l>
               <l>That borrows all her influence from the Sun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sparks and Beaus will ſurely prove our Friends,</l>
               <l>For their good Breeding muſt make them commend</l>
               <l>What Billet Deux ſo e're a Lady ſends.</l>
               <l>She knew old Thread-bare Topicks would not do,</l>
               <l>But Beaus a Species thinks it ſelf ſtill new,</l>
               <l>And therefore ſhe reſolved to Coppy you.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:6"/>
            <head>EPILOGE,</head>
            <byline>Spoken by Miſs <hi>Croſs.</hi>
            </byline>
            <lg>
               <l>KInd hearted City Wives, if any here,</l>
               <l>Was not <hi>Oliva</hi>'s Virtue too ſevere,</l>
               <l>To baulk your Expectation at that time,</l>
               <l>Kind tender Citts wou'd be a Mortal Crime;</l>
               <l>Our Gallants were undone, ſhou'd you but prove</l>
               <l>Her Apes in Virue, as you'r theirs in Love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for our Poeteſs— Lard, no Virgin ever</l>
               <l>Reſigned ſo baſhfully her darling Treaſure,</l>
               <l>She ſweats and reddens, then turns pale for fear,</l>
               <l>See what diſorders you can give the Fair;</l>
               <l>Shou'd I ask ne're ſo much to make you kind,</l>
               <l>You'd damn or pitty as ye are inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Tho' each in private wou'd be ſworn her Lover,</l>
               <l>Scarce one true Friend the Publick will diſcover.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Beau was writ at leaſt two years ago,</l>
               <l>See how rank Weeds in Foppiſh Countreys grow,</l>
               <l>Now ſo Diminutive a Spark, alaſs,</l>
               <l>He ſcarce can ſerve to ſhew you what he was;</l>
               <l>Shou'd the next two increaſe as theſe have done,</l>
               <l>The Babel Beau might hope to touch the Sun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Did but ſound Senſe and Reaſon thrive as faſt,</l>
               <l>The Coming Age might profit by the paſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:6"/>
            <head>Perſons Repreſented.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Sir <hi>Ruſtick Good-Heart,</hi> an Ill-bred Country
Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</label> Mr. <hi>Johnſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Wilmore,</hi> his Son,</label> Mr.
<hi>Verbrugen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Wildman,</hi> his Friend,</label> Mr.
<hi>Horden.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sir <hi>Amorous Courtall,</hi>
                  </label> Mr.
<hi>Powell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Smyrna,</hi> a Turkey-Merchant,</label> Mr.
<hi>Cibber.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Pulſe,</hi> a Phyſitian,</label> M.
<hi>Penkethman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Knowlittle,</hi> a Fortune-teller,</label> Mr.
<hi>Haynes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Timothy,</hi> his Man,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ready,</hi> Servant to <hi>Wildman,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>WOMEN.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Lady <hi>Young-Love,</hi> an Old Vain Conceited
Lady,</label> Mrs. <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Marina,</hi> her Daughter,</label> Mrs.
<hi>Rogers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Belira,</hi> Secret Miſtreſs to
<hi>Wilmore,</hi>
                  </label> Mrs. <hi>Knight.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Orinda,</hi> an Affected Poeteſs,</label> Mrs,
<hi>Cibber.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Olivia, Smyrna</hi>'s Wife,</label> Mrs.
<hi>Verbrugen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Iſabella,</hi> Woman to Lady
<hi>Young-Love,</hi>
                  </label> Mrs. <hi>Cole.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Phaebe, Olivia</hi>'s Maid,</label> Mrs.
<hi>Mills.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Page.</item>
               <item>Servants.</item>
            </list>
            <p>SCENE in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51767:7"/>
            <head>THE Loſt Lover, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I. <hi>The Lady</hi> Young-Love's
<hi>Houſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman <hi>and</hi> Ready.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll ſtay here till Mr. <hi>Wilmore</hi> comes in; do you
go and ſee what's to be done at Old <hi>Smyrna</hi>'s; Deliver this Letter to
Mrs. <hi>Phebe,</hi> for her Lady: <hi>Ready,</hi> thou doſt not want
Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to corrupt a Waiting Woman's Fidelity, all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty lies in
<hi>Olivia</hi>'s nicety, but I ſhould have reaſon to have an ill Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of my ſelf if I don't prevail, when I've a Friend in her Boſom that
ſpeaks for me, and only an old jealous Husband to oppoſe me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ready.</speaker>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Phebe</hi> ſays Madam <hi>Olivia</hi> has the
ſame kindneſs for you as before ſhe was Married; but her Husband is ſo
Jealous of her, he won't ſuffer her out of his ſight Day nor Night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild</speaker>
                     <p>Poor <hi>Olivia;</hi> Thy Beauty nor Merit cou'd not make
thee happy, ſince Fortune was wanting in her favours: Thy Father buried thee
in a Rich Old Merchant's arms, and 'tis my part to try to revive thee in
mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt ſeverally.</stage>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51767:8"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Marina, <hi>and</hi> Belira, Marina <hi>in
a Travailing Dreſs.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Without repeating further Welcome to you: My Dear
<hi>Marina,</hi> How have you ſpent your time in the Country?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas rough caſt, and hung heavily upon every Spoke;
nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Park, Play, nor Baſſet-Table, to call rugged Time along;
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times indeed, when disburthen'd <hi>London,</hi> wanted new Air and
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection for her Female inhabitants, I had the Diverſion of ſeeing how
well they could reliſh Country Sparks, after being cloyd with Town Beaux.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Nature is no Idler; the Fruitful Dame loves Employment; but
pray what cou'd ſhe find out in your part of the World, for nice,
well-dreſs'd diſtinguiſhing Town-Ladies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>The thing with all the World, is being pleas'd, not who
pleaſes; my pretty young Lady <hi>Made,</hi> her Lord leaving her in a
Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, wild unfurniſh'd World of Sparks, caſt her Eyes upon ſo near a
Relation of his, that ſhe miſtook the Weſt Country for <hi>Flanders;</hi>
when undiſtinguiſhing Night had reduc'd the Senſe of Seeing, into that of
Touching.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Doubtleſs ſome believe it a Satisfaction, to prove the
Difference between Town-Art, and Country-Nature; but how does Mrs.
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſent a handſome Footman of mine, to make her a
Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſhe interrupted him in the midſt, to tell him he had a
Pretty Mouth, which cou'd be better employ'd, than in delivering his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
Meſſage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>But what of that Ill natur'd, Falſe, pretended piece of
Virtue, my Lord <hi>Rural</hi>'s ſecond Daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Married, long ſince; found a Fool to uphold her ill
Nature, in railing at Mankind, and cloak her Pleaſure in uſing them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>She did my Brother the Honour of taking that fooliſh Toy a
Maiden head from him; he courted her for a Wife, and ſhe wantonly ask'd him,
if they cou'd not love without Marrying.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Since that, ſhe granted her favours in an open Calaſh,
whilſt her Husband drove it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas the boldeſt braveſt Lover I ever heard of.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>The Glory is due to her; for when he objected her Husband,
ſhe ſaid his back had been turned a thouſand Minutes, and 'twas hard if
Fortune wou'd not take care ſecurely to allow her one of them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51767:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet none pretends more to Virtue, nor will ſooner ſwear
her Neighbours wants in Uncharitableneſs to others; and count it as a
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Defect in our
ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut all
this time I forget; where's my Mother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to an
Indian-Houſe with young <hi>Wilmore,</hi> her Spouſe that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> for new Furniture, ſhe
means every thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Gay and
I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ng as her Lover.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> it enter
into a Womans head of fifty, to look back
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ellow of Twenty, whoſe
firſt contrivance will be how to ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, her Money
excepted, and that once ſecur'd ſhe may
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, what ſeparate maintainance
he is pleas'd to allow her, and he contented to ſtarve all her life after,
for having once made too la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>aſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>If I miſtake not, ſhe intrudes a little upon your right;
you have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> all your
inclination for Mr. <hi>Wilmore.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>They indeed prepare me towards making him a very Obedient
Dutiful Daughter-in-Law.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, We'll ſpare your Modeſty a farther Confeſſion,
and let you know to morrow is the Wedding day; but there's a Misfortune untold
to you, nor cou'd your imagination gueſs at it, Sir <hi>Ruſtick
Goodheart</hi> has got my Lady <hi>Young Loves</hi> conſent for Marrying
you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſee abſence has not made my Mother better natur'd; but
i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhe plays the Fool, I
ſhall be wiſer than to imitate her; beſides, mine wou'd be ſo much
worſe, as an Old Man is always leſs inviting than a Young.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Wilmore</hi> has ſhew'd himſelf ſo generous,
that till you were ſent for he refuſed to Marry your Mother, and then too
but conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſhe ſhould ſecure your Fortune to your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſurpriſing in a Father-in-Law; but is he in Love
with her, (for I can wonder at nothing) or the Match impoſed by his Father,
for his Age ſcarce allows him to know the Value of Money enough to part with
his darling Liberty for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>She has made advances to him beyond belief; his good
breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received them Civily; whereupon ſhe has forgot nothing that cou'd
make her leſs Ugly, though Age did not fail to o'er-top it all; Nature here
was ſo unkind a Miſtreſs, as to prevail in ſpight of Art.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhou'd never have gueſs'd other; for when we are once
ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to a certain Point of time, we may e'en lay aſide Pig-water, Patches
and Curls, and be contented with leſs Admiration, ſo we meet but with more
Eſteem; but if he loves her not, what can provoke him to Marry her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51767:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Gratitude and a Neceſſitous Fortune; beſides, ſhe
has almoſt pucrhaſed him with rich preſents, which has more Eloquence in
them than all the Old Womens Tongues in <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Preſents! Sure you forget your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I know what I ſay; beſides, where have you liv'd not to
know, Money ſpeaks for an Old Woman, when her Eyes no longer can: But to
entertain you till my Lady <hi>Young-Love</hi> comes in, my Page ſhall ſing
you the laſt new Song.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <head>SONG.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>AH Dangerous Swains, tell me no more,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Thy Happy Nymph you Worſhip and
Adore;</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>When thy fill'd Eyes are ſparkling at her
Name,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>I raving wiſh that mine had caus'd the
Flame.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>If by your fire to her you can impart</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Diffuſive heat to warm another's
heart:</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Ah dangerous Swain, what wou'd the ruine
be,</hi>
                                 </l>
                                 <l>
                                    <hi>Shou'd you but once perſuade you burn for
me.</hi>
                                 </l>
                              </lg>
                              <stage>
                                 <hi>Enter Lady</hi> Young Love, Wilmore.</stage>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Bid the Coach ſet up, and let the things be brought in
here My Daughter come! God bleſs you!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>I am o'er joy'd to ſee your Ladiſhip, and to ſee you
look ſo well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Ladiſhips moſt humble Servant.</p>
                     <stage>Salutes her.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Belira,</hi> How do you like theſe figur'd Velvets;
this I deſign for the Bed and Hangings; this Violet colour ſuits agreeably
with this Buff.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt extreamly well, Madam; does your Ladiſhip deſign
a Mixture?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51767:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I had thoughts of Paining and Bordering it with this
Crimſon and Green; but that ſort of Furniture has been my averſion, ever
ſince I ſaw my odious Lady <hi>Junkers</hi> Appartment ſet forth with
Scotch Plad and Damask.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel. aſide.]</speaker>
                     <p>Confuſion! How his Eyes are fix'd on her, as if his Soul
received her Charms, and wanted pow'r to hide it!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I don't look well to day, Mr. <hi>Wilmore.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Looks in her Glaſs.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Ladiſhip can never look other.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Belira,</hi> thou won't flatter me; I have not red
enough have I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar. aſide.]</speaker>
                     <p>But from the Eyes to the Chin, and looks like the Raddle
upon a Sheep's Back.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Ladiſhip is miſtaken, I never ſaw you look
better; there's a Curl indeed out of order with the motion of the Coach; Hold,
incline your Head: So, very well, that Pink-colour'd Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſuits agreeably
with your Complexion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>But do you really think, Mr. <hi>Wilmore,</hi> I look ſo
well to Day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>He has reaſon to hope, Madam, that your Ladiſhip may
look better to morrow Night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Have you catch'd hold of that report, who made you ſo
wiſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Him that is to make your Ladiſhip ſo happy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Indeed, indeed, Mr. <hi>Wilmore,</hi> it derogates from you
to talk with Girls. When I had a Mother, I durſt never think of approaching
her without Fear and Trembling. Now a Young thing as ſoon as ever ſhe has
bid farewell to Bibs and Aprons, is ready for a Love, and thinks her ſelf
with Noiſe and Impudence, better to be liked, than her Mother with all her
Experience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Page.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Ruſtick Goodheart</hi> deſires to know if your
Ladiſhip be at leiſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Always to him; I ſhall be glad of his Company Daughter, I
have taken that care of your Fortune, as deceives not the Truſt my late Lord
repoſed in me, Sir <hi>Ruſtick Good hear:</hi> and I, have agreed upon your
Marriage; my Authority ſecures your Conſent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51767:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Marriage, Madam, is a thing I have not thought on, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 'tis a Journey for Life, and
that once conſider'd, we ought to do every thing to make it as eaſie to us
as poſſible.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Ruſtick Good Heart, Wildman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi> your Servant; where have you been
ſince dinner?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Be Dad, taking a Glaſs to this pretty Lady's health, Madam
your Servant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Your moſt humble Servant.</p>
                     <stage>[They ſalute her.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wilmore,</speaker>
                     <p>a very pretty Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I cou'd think ſo to, if 'twere not of the lateſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Give me thy Hand ſweet heart, thou'rt welcome to Town, be
Dad with all my heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Young.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What think you of a Walk in the Garden; the Lovers are
engag'd, and we wou'd leave them together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>We wait upon you.</p>
                     <stage>[<hi>Manet</hi> Sir Ruſtick <hi>and</hi> Mar</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Which doſt thou like beſt, my dear, the Town, or
Country.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>The Town, Sir, beyond Compariſon, all good Judges are of
my Opinion, I hope you are one of them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Before George not I, yet if it had not been for me you had
been there ſtill; I perſuaded my Lady to ſend for you up, and have
provided a Husband for thee, Girl, what ſay'ſt thou to a Husband,
heigh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a ſort of Creature, has not yet fallen under my
Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>All in good time, Child; I like thee ne'er the worſe for
that. You don't look like the forward things of the Town, that Marries a Man
only to Cuckold him, Ods bobs thou wilt not do that, I hope, Child.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I don't underſtand you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come, we will be better acquainted, and then thou ſhale
underſtand me, heigh: to ſay truth, the way of making Cuckolds is ſoon
underſtood.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray, Sir, at once forgive, and ſatisfie my curioſity;
have you ſpent your time moſtly in the Town or Country.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51767:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Be dad, Child, the Country; I never came to <hi>London</hi>
but in times of Parliament, which thank Heaven were not very frequent in our
late Reigns; do I look Wine your Sickly <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners,</hi> the dregs of
nothing but Pox and Wine, Hemh, — Hemb, — ſhew me any young
Fellow of them all, that can match me in Health and Vigour; neither Stone, nor
Gout, nor the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts of any Diſtemper, but love of thee, Child.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Love of me, ſure you miſtake your ſelf, one wou'd have
imagin'd it, any other under the Sun at your Age.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Why there, be-dad you'r out, there's none Lovers but us old
Fellows, the Young ones don't think it worth their time; ſhew me ſuch
another as Old Sir <hi>Fair-Love Fondling;</hi> why Child he does nothing but
look Babies in her Eyes all day, but bedad I believe he ſees but in
Imagination, unleſs he borrows the aſſiſtance of Spectacles: He ſets
her, before George, in a great Chair in the very middle of a Chamber, and
himſelf for hours together at her Feet, upon a Foot-ſtool, in admiration of
her; there's encouragement now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Belira.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lady <hi>Young-Love</hi> and her Counſel are in the
Parlor, Sir, looking over the Writings, ſhe deſires your Company.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I come, I come; Sweet Miſtriſs your Servant, till I
ſee thee again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> Sir <hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I came <hi>Marina</hi> to your deliverance, I imagin'd how
you were teiz'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>O hideous! <hi>Belira,</hi> did I think in Nature, there had
been ſuch an ill bred, awkard thing; why he's ſo great a Mouſter
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, Horns can't make him worſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>And yet my Lady <hi>Young-Love</hi> ſays you muſt Marry
him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>What with twelve thouſand Pound, a great deal of Youth, no
contemptible ſtock of Beauty, beſides an untainted Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that
out-weighs them all; believe me, <hi>Belirs,</hi> I'm not ſo far ignorant of
my own worth, to bury it in him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh you don't ruine your ſelf by the Refuſal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>That Marriage is the greateſt, and you muſt uſe all
your Intereſt with my Mother to prevent it; or reſolve to make me the
moſt unhappy Creature breathing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51767:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>All aids that are in my power you may command: But has not
your Journey tir'd you, you will not be for the Park this Evening.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>The Name has unweary'd me; I'll but change my Cloahts and be
ready for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lady <hi>Young-Lous</hi> has tir'd poor <hi>Wilmore;</hi>
he has left her to her Bonds and Conveyances, and is gone to the Park be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
wou'd not you wiſh to meet him there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Why thy queſtion? He is my Mothers, and never can be mine;
but we trifle: will you favour me with your Company, whilſt I am
Dreffing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll follow you.</p>
                     <stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> Marina.</stage>
                     <p>Yes, <hi>Marina,</hi> my Intereſt pulls too ſtrong
againſt you, to leave you a Moment to your ſelf till I have put it out of
Fortunes power to injure me,</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who truſts the fawning Jilt, muſt firſt believe,</l>
                        <l>I truſt her not, and cannot be deceiv'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>[Exit Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51767:11"/>
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I. <hi>St.</hi> James's-Park.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Smyrna <hi>and,</hi> Olivia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>PRay, Gentlewoman be pleaſed to wear your Mask, till we're
got out of this Road of Foppery; I had better have gone Ten Miles about.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord, Mr. <hi>Smyrna,</hi> 'tis ſo hot, my Mask
ſtiſles me; but where are you going? I am ſure Walking is not your
Buſineſs, eſpecially in this place.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Wife, to chuſe, that you may have the pleaſure of
comparing your old damned Jealous Husband, to theſe Gay fluttering Fops, that
ſail along by us; Here's your Gallant, Mr. <hi>Wildman,</hi> coming, put on
your Mask, I ſay; Not for the World, I warrant you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis too late, he has ſeen me, Husband, 'twill be
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Smyrna,</hi> your Servant; The fair <hi>Olivia</hi>
here! Since when is it, Sir, you have been for far reconciled to our Lewd end
of the World, to truſt this Lady amongſt us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>Hum, Sir, not too much of truſting neither, but yet, as
you ſay, 'tis a dangerous place, for an old Fellow, that has an Handſom
Wife; Have not you that Opinion of her, Mr. <hi>Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>All the World muſt allow her that Character, but Faith, my
Friendſhip to you, hinders me to think of her, as I would, if ſhe were not
thy Wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>And you, forſooth, Have not you a juſt Eſteem of Mr.
<hi>Wildman</hi>'s Merit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51767:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>As I ought, I know my Duty to you, Husband, and never had a
thought againſt it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, very well, ſince you are both ſo indifferent,
'twere no great harm, if you never ſee one another again. As to you,
Gentlewoman, 'tis Mortifying you too much, to ſuffer the Viſits of a Man,
who has not Senſe to know your Worth; And, let me tell you, Mr.
<hi>Wildman,</hi> I Love my Wife, and don't like People that ſlight her
Charms, and prefer my Friendſhip to her Beauty, therefore till you come
better prepared to do her juſtice, your Viſits will be but offenſive, and
if ever you make another, I ſhall conclude you have taken a Friends Advice.
Come, wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex. Smy.</hi> and <hi>Oliv.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Go thy ways, for an old Jealour, I wiſh be-gad, I could
ſay, Cuckold, but my honeſt Endeavours ſhall not be wanting to make thee,
that thou believeſt thy ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wilmore.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank God for my deliverance, I'm got into the open Air
again, without the incumbrance of an old Woman, who is not ſatisfied,
unleſs you confine year Eyes to the Curſe of meeting none but hers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>If thou art weary already, what wilt thou be when the
Nooſe is fixt, and no kind relieving Hand can do thee the curteſy of
unſlipping it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſs, I have given the Town reaſon to believe, I
cou'd allow <hi>May</hi> and <hi>December</hi> the two ends of time, to meet in
our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Wedlock.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>The Opinion of thy Senſe was not forfeited by that, we
always believed, thou hadſt enough to diſtinguiſh between the glittering
Metal and the Allay; But are you not reſolved to Marry my Lady
<hi>Young-Love.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>So far from it, that I wou'd run my ſelf into any other
Nooſe in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to avoid hers; <hi>Marina</hi> is the
Goddeſs here; You have doubtleſs heard her Father left her a Fortune of
12000 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr> on Condition ſhe Married with my Lady
<hi>Young-Love's</hi> Conſent, elſe Shame and Beggery to be her
Portion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>That any Man ſhou'd be ſo far wedded to the Follies of
his Wife to deſire the entailing of them upon his Poſterity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I have held a long Age of Diſſimulation with her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to permit her return to Town, and get her Fortune ſecured, 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51767:12"/>engaged my Father with the hopes of Marrying her, and
doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I ſhou'd prevail over the old Lady, if it were not for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
but this is the hardeſt part of my Confeſſion, for I think, whatſoever
Cuſtom can perſuade, that Man's a Villain, who boaſts a Lady's
Favour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Begad if our Town Ladies come to know how well thou art
principled, thou may'ſt e'en make thy own Markets amongſt them, 'tis not to
be matched in thy green years, which commonly reckons the pleaſure of telling
as the foremoſt delight in an Amour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not Beaux enough for that yet. To be ſhort then,
<hi>Beliria</hi> who you know lives with, and governs my Lady
<hi>Young-Love,</hi> did me the honour to like me, and I had reaſon to
believe my ſelf Maſter of her firſt Favours, I cou'd not ſhake off her
fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, tho' all mine was ſecretly addreſt to <hi>Marina,</hi> for
whoſe ſake I was forced to diſſemble with <hi>Belire.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Begad that was ſlavery enough, for the trouble of getting
hand ſomly rid of a Miſtreſs, is ten times more than what it coſts to
make her ſuch.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>She catch'd the diſcovery from my Eyes, and unknown to
<hi>Marina</hi> perſwaded lier Mother to ſend her into the Country, then to
confound me further, the old Lady grew fond of me, <hi>Belira</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it
into her Head, that it would Marry her, by which means, ſhe conſtantly
ſecured her ſelf of ſeeing me, being in the ſame Houſe, and
reaſonably thought, the intereſt ſhe had in my Heart, ran no hazard, by
beſtowing my Perſon upon an old Woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Then how comes in, ſhe has ſuffered <hi>Marina</hi> to
return, for I perceive ſhe manages at pleaſure,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas conditionally, I Married my Lady <hi>Young-Love</hi>
to morrow, and conſented that <hi>Marina</hi> ſhould be beſtowed upon my
Father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>And how do you think to evade either.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis for that reaſon I make this diſcovery to engage
your aſſiſtance, <hi>Belira</hi> will not ſuffer her to ſign for her
Daughters Portion, till the moment of Execution, but my preſent
uneaſineſs is to entertain <hi>Marina,</hi> I have ordered Muſick and
Dancing after Supper, if poſſible engage <hi>Belira</hi> in your Affairs,
that ſhe may not concern her ſelf with mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>You have ordered your own without conſidering my
applications to <hi>Belira</hi> may ruine me with <hi>Orinda.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51767:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Quite contrary, that Coquet never likes a Man ſo well as
when he does not ſeem to be fond of her, truſt my Opinion; beſides 'twere
no Obligation if you did not run a little hazard for your Friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall command me, and now I conſider, I'le bring Sir
<hi>Amorous Courtall,</hi> who is Fop e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ough, to think all Women that have fine Cloaths Beauties; him I
deſign for the old Lady, if ſhe ſhou'd happen to like him 'twere no ill
way of getting rid of her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>That will be admirable, but be ſure ply <hi>Beliria</hi>
cloſe, ſhe's handſom enough to reward your pains, and becauſe of her
intereſt with my Lady <hi>Young-Love,</hi> the only Enemy I can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend,
— They are come into the Walk, we'll meet them at the next turn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Wil. Wild.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Marina <hi>and</hi> Belira;
<hi>meeting</hi> Orinda <hi>they ſalute.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Lad'ſhips moſt joyful humble Servant, you'r
wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to Town; how long have you done it the honour to grace it with your
preſence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>But to day, Madam, I'm pleaſed at the good fortune of
meeting you ſo ſoon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Beliria</hi> your Servant, O Gud I've been at the
Play-houſe, where there has been the odiouſeſt Play, ſo dull, that o'
my Conſcience, I ſhan't abide to ſet my foot in it again this Twelve
Month.</p>
                     <stage>Take ſnuff this time.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I believe there was very little Company there this Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
how come you to prefer that Diverſion to <hi>Hide-Park?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>O Gud, you may very well ask <hi>Beliria,</hi> for 'twas no
choice of mine, an Alderman's Wife and Daughter did me the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to
Dine with me, and preſs'd me beyond decency to go with them; O Jeſu, what a
vexation 'tis to be with thoſe preciſe ſort of People, that wou'd not go
out of their Road, tho' to be leſs odious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>They were famouſly ſet out, I warrant you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>O moſt unſuitably, the very ſight of their Trappings
wou'd have made you died of heat, of all things I hate Winter Cloaths in
Summer; what ſay you <hi>Beliria?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>That there are a ſort of People that think Finery never
out of ſeaſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51767:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orin.</speaker>
                     <p>Lard, <hi>Marina,</hi> I finiſh't a Copy of Verſes
laſt night, which I have ſent to half a ſcore of my Friends for their
approbation, I beſtow'd the laſt upon admirable Sir <hi>Amorous
Courtal,</hi> but I'le ſend you one of them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l not fail.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>Lard, Madam, what do you take me for? <hi>Beliria</hi>
muſt come in too for a Judge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray, what was the Subject?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>I know none ſo Entertaining as her ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>O, Madam, your moſt grateful Servant, 'twas upon the
different Addreſſes I have had made to me of late; O Jeſu, ſuch a glut
of Foppery and Mankind; I long to breath a little of the Country Air, that I
may get rid of this Town Lumber, and entertain my Muſe alone with the
reflections of what ſhe has left behind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>But, who is that Sir <hi>Amorous Courtall,</hi> he's
ſprung up ſince my reign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>O Gud, a very pretty Gentleman, <hi>Marina,</hi> ſo Airy,
ſo well Dreſt, ſo Handſom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>See how Opinions differ, if you'l take mine,
<hi>Marina,</hi> he's the moſt out-caſt Fop in Nature, he once made the
Campagne, but all he remembers of it, is running to <hi>Breda,</hi> which has
given him fears enough to keep at home all his life after.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Orinda,</hi> Will you favour me with your Company to
night, we have Muſick and Dancing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le wait upon you anon, 'tis my Lady Junket's Viſiting
day, and ſhe'l never pardon me, if I omit my Devoir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>O, that old Goſſipping thing, ſhe'l never have loſt
the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of youth, but wiſhes ſo well too't, ſhe'l bring young
loving things together in ſpight of their Hearts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>Fye <hi>Beliria,</hi> Gude I hate you, for being ſo
cenſorious, becauſe ſhe allows the freedom of her Apartment to Quality of
both Sexes; A Lady of her age can't be friendly or ſo, but preſently ſhe
is thought procuriſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>O, very friendly, and then ſo grateful, one Treat ſhall
make her yours all her life after.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51767:14"/>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Amorous Courtall, Wildmore,
<hi>and</hi> Wildman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Ladies, your humble Servant, 'tis a delicate Evening.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, your Servant, ſee <hi>Beliria, Orinda</hi> is
ſtealing away, go after, and bring her back.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I have ill Nature enough to break an Appointment, and I
fancy here is one.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> after <hi>Orinda.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>To <hi>Mar.</hi> I have that to ſay which it concerns you
to know, favour me but with an opportunity after Supper, and let
<hi>Beliria</hi> know nothing of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>In the Garden l'le expect you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Ten thouſand ages, till then, O <hi>Marina,</hi> do not
fail me, my Heart will ſuffer unſpeakably if you ſhou'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mor.</speaker>
                     <p>No more, take my word I'le be there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Orinda <hi>and</hi> Beliria.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ori.</speaker>
                     <p>O Jeſu, ſure <hi>Beliria</hi> you have loſt your
ſenſes, who wou'd be ſeized thus.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Together, and ſo thoughtful, I ſee the growing evil.</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me be nothing, Madam, if ever I ſaw any thing ſo
killing as your Eyes, they have Charms, my Heart never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
before.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Yours is a general gallantry to the whole Sex, Sir
<hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orin.</speaker>
                     <p>Lard, Sir. <hi>Amorous,</hi> what a loſs ſhou'd we have
had, if you had made the Campagne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſs I ſtaid in pure Charity to the fair
Sex, to expoſe them, by my abſence, was an inhumanity my Heart cou'd not
agree to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I fancy, Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> you are very fortunate in
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me expire, Madam, if I have any reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain,
but thoſe fair Eyes, makes me forget, every thing but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſwear Mrs. <hi>Wildman,</hi> you talk pleaſantly, come
<hi>Marina,</hi> ſhall we not be going?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>When you pleaſe; <hi>Orinda</hi> we muſt not leave you
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51767:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l give me leave to wait on you to your Coach,
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> not ſo faſt, come back, 
<stage>[<hi>Ex. Monet. Wild.</hi> Sir <hi>Am</hi>]</stage>
I've a word with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pax on you, let me go, I muſt wait upon the Ladies, 'tis
ſuch an omiſſion, that I ſhall never be pardon'd, nor deſerve the
Eſteem of a Gentleman amongſt them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>You may appologize for that anon, I call'd you back, to give
you a little Advice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Be ſudden then, I cannot live, divided from
<hi>Marina.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>The old fire, that flames upon ſight of every new Face,
but I deſign you for another, who exceeds her in advantages, as much as you
do all the Play-houſe Beaus in Dreſs and Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No ill Compariſon; who is it? I dye to know.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild,</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt then, ſhe's prodigious rich, wears extravagant
fine Cloaths, and has the beſt way of putting them on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O, of all things, I love a Lady well Dreſt, let me be
nothing, if one that is other, does not look mean, and as if ſhe were to be
loved according.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Then ſhe's Amorous, and will no doubt be preſently taken
with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Pſhaw, Pax, ſo they all tell me, I cou'd have bated her
that part of the Character, 'tis ſurfeiting.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Her Fortune however is enviting, if you apply your ſelf to
her, ſhe's rich enough to reward your labour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me expire, if thou doſt not talk ſcandalouſly, I
hope 'tis not Matrimony thou hint'ſt at.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, you're too much a Man of Mode, to make the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
uneaſie to you; a Civil Husband, and ſo forth, is all that a Wife can
rationally expect from you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Gad, now I think on't, Cold Civility to a Wife, gives one a
good air, let me dye, if I cou'd be fond of an Angel that I was once Married
to, but to be ſeen abroad with her, were an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance, I ſhou'd never
forgive my ſelf for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Or if it ſhou'd happen, once in an Age, I fancy, you you
wou'd make juſt ſuch meen, as my Lord <hi>Stately,</hi> and his Lady, when
they are together in one Coach at <hi>Hyde-Park.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Juſt for all the World, or let me expire, let me never
breath, if I have not been paſſionately in love with her uneaſie Frowns,
and even raviſh't to find during the whole Park time ſhe 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51767:15"/>had not beſtow'd one word, nor look, upon her Lord, one
wou'd have ſworn, but by her Frowns, ſhe had not known him to be ſo near
her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Gad, I think he matches her, his lolling back in his Coach,
without glance or motion, ſpeaks as much mortification as her ſulleneſs,
the beſt we can conclude is, that they'r heartily weary of one another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Shew me that Married Couple who are not, but then there's
good Management in thoſe Affairs, as in all others; Is it reaſonable to
diſguſt one ſelf with a Wives Company, only to oblige the Town with
Matter for remark, let her take her Coach, and leave me the freedom of my
Chariot, I'le give her the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Glaſs as we meet, paſs on and
make no uneaſie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of the heavy load intail'd upon Mortal life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſides, my Widow will ſet all uneaſineſs aſide,
and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the breach you have made in your Eſtate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>The Campaign, the Campaign <hi>Charles,</hi> let me be
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if I did not looſe Baggage to the value of 1500
<abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr> all my Dreſſing Plate, Wardrobe, and Military
Accoutrements, and was glad to ſecure my ſelf at <hi>Breda,</hi> with only
the days Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon my Back, thou art my Friend, to whom I may own
ſuch a Misfortune, let me expire, if ever I was in ſuch a Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
ſince I was born into the World.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis now Eight a Clock; do you know my Lady
<hi>Young-Loves</hi> here in the Square, any body will tell you the Houſe,
I'll meet you there at Nine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Adieu; I'll walk over the Park to my Lodgings, write an
Excuſe to an Expecting Lady, who does my Company the Honour to ſigh for it,
and then I'll be certain to wait upon you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt ſeverally.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51767:15"/>
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Knowlittle, <hi>and his Man</hi>
Timothy.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>WHy truly <hi>Tim.</hi> we have had but a ſorry Day
on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>Indifferent, Maſter, beſides thoſe that came to
inquire after Stolen Goods; the Party that wou'd know the Cauſe why ſhe did
not conceive, paid us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Look out ſome body knocks, <hi>Tim.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>O Gemini, Maſter! 'Tis Mr. <hi>Smyrna,</hi> the Turky
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, and Madam <hi>Olivia</hi> his Wife; I am very well acquainted with
her Maid, Mrs. <hi>Phaebe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace, we muſt not pretend to know them till the Stars
have been conſulted: I'll to my Study, mind your hits, <hi>Tim.</hi> and get
what intelligence you can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Smyrna, Olivia, <hi>and</hi> Tim.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyrn.</speaker>
                     <p>Where's your Maſter, Friend, I hope 'tis not too late to
ſpeak with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>In his Study, Sir; I'll go and acquaint him with your being
here; He does not uſe to appear after Sun.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Tim.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord, Husband, you are the ſtrangeſt Man in the World,
what will People think of you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyrn.</speaker>
                     <p>What, Miſtreſs, you'r afraid the Devil ſhould ſpeak
Truth, and diſcover your Abominations.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>The Devil's the Father of Lyars, how ſhou'd he ſpeak
Truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>You are the Mother of Lyars, and that Cuckold maker
<hi>Wild-man,</hi> one of your vile Diſciples.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe you heard he courted me before I was Married, you
think I muſt needs be naught with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51767:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smy.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, very Good in your ſenſe, I warrant; Naught, why
thou art not a Citizen's Wife for nothing; thou haſt more grace I truſt in
the Lord, than not to think Cuckolding thy Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band a good honeſt practicable
Thing; thoſe are naught who do it ſo awkardly that the World is acquainted
with it; nay their very Husbands, who are always the laſt in knowing the
Favours that are done them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>But ſure, you don't believe, that an ignorant block-head
of a Fortune-teller, ſhould ſpeak any thing like Truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll tell you what I believe though, Miſtriſs, in my
caſe of Enquiry your Ladiſhip can exceed all the Cunning men in
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and read our Fortunes to a Tittle; but the Devil's in't, you
won't make me as wiſe as your ſelf, but put me here upon unlawful means,
the Sin will lye at your door, Wife, you'd as good confeſs, and ſave
charges into the Bargain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>If I ſhould, I'm ſure you wou'd not believe me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>The Devil take me then; Come be quick, before Maſter
Aſtrologer comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord, Husband, what do you take me for? Why, if it were
ſo, do you think I'd be ſuch a Fool to confeſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>No; Thou'rt wiſer o'my Conſcience, but be ſure you are
as truſty to other Folks; you Women have ſhe Friends that you diſcover
your failings to, and that way the Secret comes about; 'tis for your
Intereſt, as well as mine, to keep the matter private, if 'twere but for the
ſake of preſerving your Lovers; they are ſqueamiſh amongſt ſuch a
glut of Womens Fleſh, and are diſguſted by that which has been blown
upon; but ſee the Devil appears to decide our Controverſie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Scene Opens and diſcovers</hi> Knowlittle
<hi>behind a long Table; Books, Globes, Compaſſes, Pen, Ink, Paper,</hi>
&amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Is your buſineſs with me, Friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Mr. <hi>Knowlittle,</hi> I've a doubtful Queſtion to
be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, therefore there's ſomething by way of Encouragement, only
whether my Wife do me Juſtice, you underſtand me Friend; I'm plaguily
afraid of being a Cuckold, an ignorant Cuckold, Sir, for that's all; Pray
conſult the Stars, that I may come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my good Fortune.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>We'll erect a Scheme, or as the Vulgar term it, caſt a
Figure, and give you the Opinion of the Stars thereupon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51767:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>He's Conjuring; we ſhall immediately ſee the Devil in
the Circle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you ſo ſilly to believe it, he ſeems to be a
ſorry ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Knave, that has more Will than Power to do Evil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>They ſay a Woman can out-wit the Devil, and I believe
out-Face him too — Well, Mr <hi>Knowlittle,</hi> have you done? What do
the Stars ſay, am I repreſented with Horns like Capricorn, with a certain
Tall-young Gentleman in my Figure, who does my Wife the Honour to Love her,
better than ſhe can her Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Wife, Sir, looks like a good Virtuous Lady, and your
Figure ſpeaks you to be a mighty diſſatisfy'd Perſon, a little troubled
in your Brain with Jealouſie; but either my Skill deceives me, or you have no
occaſion for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſay you Maſter <hi>Knowlittle,</hi> do you like my
Wife too? does the Stars denote me for further Cuckoldom, what encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
do they give you, to take her part for ſhe's ſo bad, not one Devil in Hell
dares do it without a Bribe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that one queſtion all you wou'd have reſolved.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay Friend, and I ſee 'tis more than thou canſt do, thou
art going to convince me of the Vanity and Folly of all thoſe who have helped
thee to deceive themſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>How, Sir, do you undervalue my Profeſſion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>O no, Sir, Your Profeſſion is a very Learned
Profeſſion; but I much doubt the Skill of the Profeſſor:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Were it not for this Virtuous, Good Lady, I cou'd ſhow you
a Proof of my Art wou'd make you tremble; yet verily it may be a means to
acquit her; how ſay you, Sir, if you dare ſtand it, I'll raiſe a Familiar
to convince you, and protect your Wife near me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd you frighten me into an Opinion of your Art, you that
can't tell a Man whether, or no, he's a Cuckold; I have no Faith in you, and
therefore dare ſtand the Worſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Knowlittle <hi>takes</hi> Olivia <hi>behind the Table and
whiſpers her, turns over his Books, uſes poſtures of Conjuration,
ſtamps with his Foot; then</hi> Tim <hi>ariſes, dreſs'd like a Fury, with
a Wand in his Hand, ſtrikes</hi> Smyrna <hi>thrice over the Head with
it,</hi> Oliva <hi>ſhreeks,</hi> Smyrana <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, looks affrighted, and
ſinks down as ſueh in a Chair.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <l>From Hell's deep Center, hither am I come,</l>
                     <l>To warn thee, Mortal of thy heavy doom;</l>
                     <l>Thy Wife is Chaſte, yet ſhalt thou not believe,</l>
                     <l>Thy Viſionary Doubts, thy Mind deceive;</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51767:17"/>
                     <l>Therefore remain accurſt, and may'ſt thou find,</l>
                     <l>Thy conſtant plague, in thy ſuſpicious Mind.</l>
                     <stage>Deſcends.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Knowlittle,</hi> accept of this Gratuity; my Husband
faints! Lord, I wiſh his fears have not taken away his uſe of Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
He'll never remember what the Devil ſaid to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, Sir; How fares it with you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord! How do you do, dear Husband? I'm frighted out of my
Wits; I'll never venture to the Devil again with you, you ſhall e'en go by
your ſelf, next time for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay poor Wife; as thou ſay'ſt thou wilt, I believe, for
ſake me in all Perils; but is he gone are you ſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Gone; Yes, Sir, what do you think; by vertue of my Art I can
lay as well as raiſe— This 'twas to be incredulous, and undervalue the
Myſteries of Knowledge; I was ſorced to uſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary means to
convince you: O the Blindneſs snd Stony-heartedneſs of the Ignorant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray let a Coach be call'd— I'm very ill— but
Maſter <hi>Fortune-Teller,</hi> your Skill in the <hi>Black-Art,</hi>
ſhan't make me believe my Wife the Fairer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis the Capricio of all Old Men, Jealous of every thing
that's Younger than themſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, poor Lady; Heaven endow you with Patience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>—
There's a Coach, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Is there, come Wife; good Night Friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, your Servant; Madam your Servant: <hi>Tim.</hi> wait
upon the Gentry to the Coach.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> Smy. Oliv. Tim.</stage>
                     <p>Verily this Evening has helped the Morning, and both
together made a good Day, few better.—</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Tim.</stage>
                     <p>Now, <hi>Tim.</hi> thou didſt it admirably. </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Maſter, did not I; He little thinks, that from my
hiding place, I over-heard all he ſaid; but how did the Habit ſet upon
me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>As like as the Devil cou'd be, every one in there way,
<hi>Tim.</hi> all Trades have their Cheats, and this is to be ſaid for ours,
we do it with their own conſents.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tim.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, Maſter, better this than worſe, every thing wou'd
fain live, and we do but our honeſt endeavours thereto.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Know.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, let's go in and pray, to morrow may but prove as good
a Day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51767:17"/>
                  <head>SCENE II. <hi>Lady</hi> Young Loves
<hi>Houſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Ruſtick, Wildman, <hi>and</hi>
Belira.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>TO Morrow, Sir <hi>Ruſtick</hi> is the happy day.</p>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi> Be-gad, I long for the Sack-poſſet,
and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Stocking; that was the Faſhion when I was Married, and a
good Sociable one too; I mean to make uſe of it ſtill. He, he, he! I have
bin telling her, how eager all the young Fellows will be of hitting the Bride
in the Face; but be-dad, I hope I ſhall hit her better ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe;
before <hi>George,</hi> I'll try to get a Nap in this Chair, and Dream of to
Morrow, before to Morrow comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Ruſtick</hi> is falling aſleep over his Wooing.
When we force Nature beyond her ſelf, ſhe muſt return for a recruit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Be-gad Madam! You don't know what an Inſipid Fellow I am
this way; I never Love taking fruitleſs pains: If I had not a real
Inclination for you; the Devil take me, I if wou'd pretend it: For where's the
ſatisfaction of diſſembling; when that, which ſhou'd be a reward to our
endeavours, diſguſts our Inclinations.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>You Men of the Town, never value a Woman for her ſelf;
'tis only to increaſe the Wretched number, tho' your ſelves are never the
better for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>That's only ſeen amongſt the Looſe, Idle part of
Mankind; who not ſetting a value upon their own Reputations, think it no
fault to Expoſe a Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, not diſputing any further your Talent of Secrecy,
what Security can you give of your Sincerity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Charms, and the opinion the World has of my Senſe:
Be-gad, wou'd you have a more undoubted one? If a Woman be very handſome, and
meets with a Man who has Wit enough to know and value it; the Conſequence
ſpeaks it ſelf, and needs no Corroborating Evidence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, enough of this to Night; I receive you for my Lover,
and as ſuch, you muſt do me what Service I deſire. <hi>Wilmore</hi> and
you, are mighty Friends. Has he told you nothing of his concern for
<hi>Marina?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>He's to Marry her Mother — Beſides Child! I never
care to hear thoſe ſort of ſecrets, for fear they ſhou'd expect mine in
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>However indifferent your are, I'll tell you one; tho' the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <pb n="22" facs="tcp:51767:18"/>runs of to Morrow. <hi>Wilmore,</hi> muſt Marry
my Lady <hi>Young Love</hi> privately this Night, and if you pleaſe, you
ſhall have the Honour of beſtowing her upon him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Commands wou'd make greater difficulties eaſie; but
Pox, why this haſte, to bring a young Fellow into ſlavery? Does he know the
Deſign?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>She carried him hence to tell him: I can't imagine how
ſhe'l bring it about; for I fancy, one muſt be a good deal out of
Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to let a young Fellow know, one has a mind to lye with him, one
Night ſooner than he deſign'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay, or deſired; for if I were to be Mr.
<hi>Bridgroom,</hi> that wou'd be my Caſe always with an old Woman: But where
is he now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Shut up with her in her Cloſet; if you'l ſtay a Moment,
I'll go ſee what's become of 'em.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Belira.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>If we don't take care, this Gipſey will be too cunning for
us all; Pox take Sir <hi>Amorous;</hi> Where can he ſtay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Iſabel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                     <p>Is Madam <hi>Belira</hi> here? My Lady Enquires for her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>No Child, ſhe's juſt gone; but here's a Friend of yours,
wou'd be glad to ſee you at my Lodgings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                     <p>I aſſure you Mr. <hi>Wildman,</hi> you are miſtaken in
me; I wou'd not be a Whore, if you wou'd keep me a Coach and Six Horſes, to
tend me all days of my Life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, now I'm ſure you lye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Iſabel.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wilmore.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Pox take all old <hi>Amorous</hi> Women; I ſtinck of
Petter as bad as her ſelf: I fancy it to be like our Perriwiggs, that retain
the ſcent of Tobacco, after being in a City Coffee-Houſe. <hi>Belira</hi>
has told you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes — Have you ſeen <hi>Marina?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Where ſhou'd I ſee her, in her Mother's Cloſet?
Be-gad, you wou'd have laught your ſelf to Death, to hear her break the
buſineſs to me. She was in ſo good a Humour, that had I not wanted
Witneſſes, ſhe wou'd have ſign'd, without conſulting her Oracle,
<hi>Belira.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVild.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis pity, the Poor Lady ſhou'd be diſappointed of a
Husband; Sir <hi>Amorous</hi> ſhall Marry her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>But how? I don't think it feaſible.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVild.</speaker>
                     <p>We'll try to turn our Modern Comedy-Plots into good,
ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, earneſt, and make her Marry one for another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>Impoſſible! <hi>Belira</hi> is her ſhadow, and not to
be deceived. They ſtay Supper for us; my appointment holds with
<hi>Marina;</hi> the Muſick will amuſe the reſt of the Company; if
poſſible, don't let <hi>Beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> follow us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51767:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVild.</speaker>
                     <p>If ſhe follows you, I'll follow her, I aſſure you, for
I've talked my ſelf, into a kind of liking of her; but we muſt not leave
the old Gentleman behind us. Sir, Sir! How ſound he ſleeps? He's taking up
his Rents before-hand, and providing for to Morrow Night, which he Fancies will
be no good one of reſt to him: They ſtay Supper for you Sir
<hi>Ruſtick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Supper, why, what's a Clock?</p>
                     <stage>Yawns and wakes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>Near ten, Sir: Shall we wait upon you down?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I had rather you ſhou'd wait upon me up, Sir, a good Bed
in my Country is worth ten Suppers; but be-dad, I muſt not tell my
Miſtreſs ſo till I am her Maſter. Come along.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>We wait upon you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Lady</hi> Young Loves <hi>Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Scene opens, and diſcovers Lady</hi> Young Love,
Marina, <hi>Sir</hi> Amorous Courtall, Wilmore, Wildman, Orinda, Belira.
<hi>Song and Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dancing.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>WHere's Sir <hi>Ruſtick,</hi> that he has not honoured us
with his Company?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>I left him taking a Grace-Cup with your Ladyſhips
Chaplain. Mr. <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> will be too hard for him, they are ſo
uſed to their Sanctified Wine they can ſwallow a large ſhare of our
unhallowed Juice of the Grape. Be pleaſed to know my Friend, Sir <hi>Amorous
Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit after</hi> Marina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>As ſuch I muſt ever value and eſteem him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Your Ladyſhip<hi>'s</hi> moſt Obedient Servant; let me
Expire, if ever I ſaw any thing ſo taking as your Ladyſhip<hi>'s</hi>
Civility.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Lard Sir <hi>Amorous!</hi> Do you conſider whoſe in the
Company? Theſe young Ladies will have reaſon to Quarrel at your Judgment,
or rather I ſhou'd be diſpleaſed at your inſincerity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me expire Madam, if ever I ſaw any thing ſo ingaging
as your Air. O that Dreſs, that Dreſs Madam! The Devil take me if the
Drawing Room in all its Birth-night finery, can ſhew us any thing equal to
it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I wiſh I had but as good a Title to the reſt of your
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations; but time was, when they might have paſſed upon me with
leſs injuſtice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Be-gad Madam, no time like the preſent: The Sun is not in
his glory till he is mounted to the Meridian, let me dye; if I can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
your ſelf, cou'd ever exceed your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51767:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Lard, Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> your'e extream Courtly! How
unfortunate have I bin till now, in wanting your Acquaintance! I never had ſo
ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den an eſteem for any one. O! I Love a well bred Man, in my Soul
— Good Breeding— There's no Charm exceeds it. Pray Sir
<hi>Amorous</hi> have you not bin abroad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Yes Madam, I have fetch't the Tour of all the Courts in
<hi>Italy,</hi> made ſome ſmall reſidence in <hi>Spain,</hi> but their
Gravity diſguſted me, and therefore made haſte to paſs into
<hi>France,</hi> which had every thing that a well bred Gentleman cou'd
deſire, either to Inſtruct or Entertain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Lard, 'tis ſtrange! I durſt have ſworn that very thing
by your Air, your janty, way of Dreſs, your Perriwig. Oh Jeſu! How
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing the Curls fall to cover your Face, and leave us almoſt nothing
beſides to Contemplate. Ah! how far you exceed all that ever I ſaw in the
Art of Powdering. <hi>Belira,</hi> don't you think Sir <hi>Amorous</hi>
Dreſſes extreamly well?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Undoubtedly, Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> I beg your Pardon I did
not ſee you ſooner— Heigh, this is Gallantry indeed! What a new
Dreſs!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>The Devil take thy Foppery; was it for this, thou madeſt
us ſtay for thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I had a Misfortune, juſt as I was croſſing to my
Lodging, a filthy Carman daſh't me moſt intolerably, a juſt reward for
being on foot in the dirty Street; I was forc'd to change my Cloaths before I
was fit for this ſhining Aſſembly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orin.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> your moſt devoted, Admirer—
Lard, my Lady <hi>Young Love,</hi> did you ever ſee any <hi>Steenkirk</hi>
have that Air? Never cou'd Madam, the Princeſs <hi>de Conty,</hi> have hoped
a Copy, ſo tranſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ng
the Original.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Tis all of a Piece, all Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> in a word;
all that can be named, the fine Gentleman, the Courtier, the Something beyond
all, the Modern expreſſive word of Beau.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me expire, if your Ladyſhip has not the beſt
Judgment. is not my Sword-knot extreamly fine and juſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orin.</speaker>
                     <p>O, of a moſt raviſhing length— What is Faſhion,
for well bred People, If, as Mr. <hi>Bays</hi> ſays, we don't top our
parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Ladyſhip<hi>'s</hi> unacquainted with one Sir of
<hi>Amorou</hi>'s Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; he Dances to a Miracle, and carried it from
all the Quality at the laſt Court Ball.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>A Corant or Minuet, Madam, I am no higher Dancer: Will your
Ladyſhip do me the Honour of a Minuet?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> I muſt beg your Pardon, if I ſhare
the Dance, I ſhall loſe the entire Proſpect of your Perſon;
<hi>Belira,</hi> if ſhe pleaſes ſhall oblige us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVild.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, be-gad Madam, you ſhan't go till Sir <hi>Amorous</hi>
has done with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Eternal Impertinence, they are both miſſing, and
undoubtedly <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51767:19"/>together. Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> I'm not in
Humour, and ſhall make but an ill Figure, <hi>Orinda</hi> will do much
better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let my be nothing, Madam, if ſhe has not ten times more
Chagrin in her Looks than your Ladyſhip. I muſt not be refuſed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous</hi> Dances in Perfection.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Dance.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVild.</speaker>
                     <p>I told your Ladyſhip his Talent, I was ſure you wou'd
not find me in a miſtake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>The Dance done,</hi> Belira <hi>goes out.</hi> Wildman
<hi>follow her.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Orin.</speaker>
                     <p>So ſlighting, ſhe has Debauch'd him from me. O I can't
hold my Muſe! Muſe go Lament the Misfortune.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For to Love is Noble frailty; but Poor ſin,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When once we fall to Love, unlov'd again.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Orinda.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O your Ladyſhip flatters me, or let me dye! But to ſay
what has bin ſaid before, Blows from hands ſo ſoft, who wou'd not
bear!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> you are a Judge of Decorum and
Decency; what ſay you to walking in, and ſeeing the Bridall Bed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I'll follow your Ladyſhip through the World; but I ſhall
expire in ſeeing the place where my Happineſs is to be Sacrificed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>O Jeſu! 'Tis a thouſand pities ſo pretty a young
Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhou'd have an uneaſie Moment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SCENE</hi> Changes to the Garden.</head>
                  <stage>Wilmore, <hi>and</hi> Marina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>GRant, I diſpenſe with that one Form of our Sex,
disbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Lover, when he firſt tells us he is ſuch; how can you avoid
my Mother, or delay her expectations? <hi>Belira,</hi> whoſe reaſons I
could not comprehend before; will do all that's neceſſary to ruine our
intelligence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>If nothing elſe can ſecure me, your Denial muſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Twelve Thouſand Pounds is a Forfeiture too great to oblige
an Enemy with. I hear <hi>Belira</hi>'s voice, ſhe muſt not ſee us
together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Marina.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Belira, <hi>followed by</hi>
Wildman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>But why do you follow me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>But why do you fly me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Marina</hi> ſhot that way. I ſee <hi>VVilmore</hi>
at the bottom of the Walk, I have buſineſs with him; oblige me, and leave
us together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVild.</speaker>
                     <p>You Command me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit.</hi> Wildman.</stage>
                  <stage>[Wilmore <hi>comes forward.</hi>]</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>Here ſo late <hi>Belira?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51767:20"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel..</speaker>
                     <p>I come in ſearch of you, the Bride expects you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>To Night! It muſt not be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame thing as to Morrow, the ſooner 'tis over the
better; for in theſe caſes our fears are the worſt part of our
puniſhment. Was not <hi>Marina</hi> with you? ſhe is wanted. Sir
<hi>Ruſtick</hi> has drank himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Matrimonial Temper, and Mr.
<hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> Swears twelve at Night, is as Canonical as that at
Noon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Belira,</hi> have you Loved me!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Has not my Ruin told you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Then do you Love me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, to ſee you happy— But the Mask is off, and thou
canſt Cheat no more, and I no more believe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>You never Loved, but now abhor me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>You reproach me with what I wou'd be; do not, do not rouze
the Woman in me, I wou'd be Calm to Night and ſee you Married.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>Rather ſee me Buried.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Perhaps ſo— Cou'd the remembrance of my Wrongs but
ſleep with thee, I wou'd not Envy thee a quiet Grave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewel, we part for ever, I'll leave the Town this
Minute.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>At leaſt, Sir, if you will not Marry your ſelf, but
unkindly leave your Bride thus in the longing Moment; do your Father the honour
to grace his Marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>What have I done, that you ſhou'd wiſh to make me
Wretch'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>What haſt thou left undone to make me ſuch?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Reputation yet ſtands fair, and uleſs your own
Indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betrays you the Secret ſhall be ſuch, with me for ever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>But thy heart, Traytor, thy perjur'd Heart; tell me, how
ſhall I get it back?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Never this way, I aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis given for gone then— Go— Live as Wretch'd
as I can make you, I'll think no more upon you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Where, Madam, are you going?</p>
                     <stage>going.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>To a Wedding, Sir, <hi>Marina</hi>'s Wedding; you ſay we
muſt not Dance at yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Rather of the two <hi>Belira,</hi> but why to Night?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>All Bridgrooms are not as backward as your ſelf; your
Father has the ſtart of you, in deſire as well as years, he is impatient of
his Happineſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>You are Peeviſh <hi>Belira;</hi> does your Love make you
Jealous?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I have none, the <hi>Moor</hi> has taught me better; no
longer doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, away at once with Love and Jealouſie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Then 'tis Spite diſturbs you: In what have I deſerved
it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Look in thy falſe perfidious Heart, and take my Anſwer
thence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51767:20"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſpeaks of nothing you can quarrel with.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I will ſtay and argue with thee, how often haſt
thou told, thou coud'ſt for ever Love me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I told you that I cou'd, not that I wou'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Poor Caviller, thoſe who can jeſt with Oaths, can play
with Words— You'l come after and wiſh the Bride Joy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>We muſt not part thus, you were not uſed to fly my
Arms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>By all that's good, he has got the ſorry cunning of our
Sex; juſt ſo does a Wife when her Husband has caught her falſe, the
gilting Creature cries, Do you believe it Spouſe? you do not uſe to be ſo
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind— Ha, ha, ha— Let me Laugh, tho' 'tis maliciouſly; go on,
I'm in the Vein of Audience; let me hear ſome diſagreeable Truths, and how
well thou canſt turn Woman; <hi>Marina</hi> is at ſtake before you, do it
handſomely; I wou'd be fortified in my Averſion, and have my hate
implacable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis Barbarous to inſult, where you ſhou'd rather
pity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I do, let all the World be judge elſe; nay, do more than
Pity, I wou'd prevent your Ruin, and ſtop the Paſſage up to your undoing,
wou'd ſave you from the Ills, nay, Scorns of Poverty, keep your Friends
ſuch, and put it in your Power to be one by ſtill Preſerving you: The
Worlds opinion, who judge of Merit but by Fortunes Favours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>We know the Extent of your Generoſity: But ſerve me as I
wou'd be ſerv'd, <hi>Belira.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>I thought this was your way: I miſtook you for him that
was to Marry my Lady <hi>Young Love</hi>— But I'll go look for
certainties within.</p>
                     <stage>Going.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Come back <hi>Belira,</hi> 'tis my laſt Call: I wou'd
ſatisfie thy Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſh Revenge, and let thee ſee me Curſt by any other
way than Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Marriage— Take my Sword— Thy Malice can ſupply
thy want of uſe, deſpight can furniſh ſtrength, and too often thou
haſt found the way to my unhappy Heart to miſs it now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha, in Love to dying! By all that's good, turn'd
<hi>Hero:</hi> Your Miſtreſs, Sir, is much obliged— Keep your Sword,
it may be a Fortune better worth than all your Fathers Lands; there's Wars
abroad, you may employ it in, 'twill keep your Wife from wanting here at
Home.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Am I indeed your Scorn, Proud, Fantaſtick Woman; thy
liking was foul Luſt; not Love: That gentle Name brings Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but
thou— Let me not think upon thee, for fear it force my Tongue to
ſomething worſe, than ſhou'd be ſaid of Ladies; I've ſerved it
ſeems, as long as you cou'd like, and now you chuſe another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Wou'd it were come to that, I wou'd exchange thee, for 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51767:21"/>the laſt of Men, and think the Bargain Cheap, wou'd part
with all that goodly Form, for honeſt Uglineſs, and think it fairer; thy
Youth for Age, and Doat upon his Doatage— So in return I found but Truth,
mark well that word, that word has Charms thou never kneweſt, and which
out-weighs thine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Belira,</hi> thou haſt power to read my Soul; thy
Magick Spells are irreſiſtable. How haſt thou found this Failing in my
Vertue, which I not knowing of, my Wants cou'd never miſs till now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank my Wit, Natures beſt Gift— I've ſeen your
ſhunting poor deſigning Arts, to wave this Marriage and promote another.
Your care too, of <hi>Marina</hi>'s Fortune falſly guilded with the weak
pretence of Generoſity; 'twas not doubled thick enough for me: But becauſe
Doubts never ſhou'd condemn the Man I Loved, I wou'd not ſeem to doubt till
I was certain; therefore no more diſſembling, 'tis vain, <hi>Marina</hi>
never ſhall be yours; and if you cou'd not think it an unhappineſs, I fain
wou'd keep you mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>Give me this Night to think in, I'll promiſe nothing, but
this: I'm Grateful where I am obliged.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>To ſhew your Power, I will; my Lady <hi>Young Love</hi>
through my perſuaſion deſigned this the Marriage Night; I'll excuſe you
to her, but not one word or thought of <hi>Marina,</hi> for in that Moment
ſhe ſhall be beſtowed upon another; I wou'd divide the World, rather than
you ſhou'd meet; I hope to Morrow, we may give you joy; this Night I find but
little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Belira.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Leſs thou haſt left behind, O the curſe of Lewdneſs!
What Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<hi>'s</hi> Fair after we find her Faulty? What Lady Innocent, when
no longer Chaſte? Or who ſo vain to hope for Honour, or for Pity from that
Soul who wants it for her ſelf?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild</speaker>
                     <p>What I hear 'tis deferrd, there's no hopes of Poſſet.
<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ria</hi> has
diſſmiſs'd me till to Morrow, ſhe's gone to your Bride; by this time
Sir <hi>Amorous</hi> has ſupplanted you, he is ſhut up with her, and has
impudence enough to bid fair for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>VVil.</speaker>
                     <p>They talk of Eating againſt ones Stomach, but no Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
is ſo nauſeous, as what I'm in danger of, <hi>Belira</hi> catch'd me in the
A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ion; and Faith, a ſinner
muſt have more impudence than I, who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> deny matter of Fact.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51767:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Be gad, I have Pimpt to a fair end: What to let a Woman
out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit thee? How cou'd you once think of being ſincere to one, whoſe
Intereſt runs counter to yours? I would have diſſembled as much Love as I
had Averſion; nay Counterfeited my firſt deſires, and ſuffered her, to
believe ſhe had preſerved the Conqueſt of me now, that I might have
Triumphed over her all my life after.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Very well, I am railed at on all ſides.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt this Moment in thy Face, all the Mortification
of poor Lenten Penitents, and lookſt more akin to the Spirit than the
Fleſh. I believe thou art not in the condition of Wedlock. Confeſs your
Misfortune to my Lady <hi>Young-Love,</hi> I know no reaſon, why a Man
ſhou'd pretend falſe Courage, when by it he runs himſelf into an
inconveniency, he might have otherways avoided.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Amorous.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith, if lying, diſſembling and flattering, can
deſerve her, I have done it. After we parted, I underwent the Mortification
of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which has the better fitted me for that of Matrimony; 'twas
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for me, to have juſt got out of the Baliffs hands, to be able
to go through with her, or elſe let me expire, if I cou'd have done it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>But what's the Conſequence, Sir <hi>Amorous?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No more, than deferring the Marriage. The Duce take me if I
don't think it Exceeds all <hi>Hercules</hi>'s Labours, to be able to
perſwade a Widow to lye alone, when ſhe is reſolved to have a
Bed-fellow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Ready.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>The next Affair ſhall be reſolv'd in your Chamber, where
I'll wait Sir <hi>Amorous</hi> and you in a Minute.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay if you wou'd be private, I'm diſcreet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me be nothing, if he has not ſome melting Billet, I
know it by his very Air. Good Fortune to thee <hi>Charles.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Sir</hi> Amorous, Wil.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reads,</hi> Hum! to Morrow Morning like a Phiſician.
<hi>Ready,</hi> where had you this Letter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ready.</speaker>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Phoebe</hi> brought it to your Lodgings. She ſays
her Maſter has bin at the Fortune-tellers, to Enquire, whether your Honour
had made him a Cuckold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>I am ſorry, the Devil cou'd not anſwer him in the
Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: She writes me word that <hi>Symrna</hi>'s ſick with his fright,
and that I may paſs upon him for a Phyſician; however, I believe my skill
lyes moſt <hi>Olivias</hi> way. <hi>Ready,</hi> go and knock up my
Apothecary; borrow his Velvet Coat with the great Gold Buttons. A few hard
words, of Plebotomy, Purgative, Laxative, and I ſhall be ſet up in my
Profeſſion, <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51767:22"/>and look like any Collegiate Doctor of them
all— Why then, the Devil take me if I don't go— Now the matter's
brought to Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I'll not fall aſleep over the Brazen Head, when it
ſhou'd anſwer me. Yes.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I'll watch the falling of the Golden Shower,</l>
                        <l>And reap my Harveſt in the ſhining Hour.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Olivia<hi>'s Chamber.</hi> Olivia <hi>and</hi>
Phoebe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>BY my Troth, Madam, if all Ladies ſhould follow your
Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Solitude wou'd make them ſoon turn honeſt; and then where were
the Employment for Wit and Scandal? You need not be in ſuch a Terror of my
Maſter, he ſleeps as ſound as a Top; and ſhould Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi>
come in the Interim, we might introduce him to your Ladyſhip without his
being the wiſer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>I hear knocking at the Gate; go ſee if your Maſter be
awake. Why do I tremble thus? I neither diſtruſt my Vertue, nor his Care of
it. Yet a ſecret Guilt condemns me, becauſe I exceed in Form. If the Shadow
of an Injury gives ſuch Uneaſineſs, what do they ſuffer by Remorſe
who actually offend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman <hi>like a Phyſician,</hi>
Phoebe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>My Life! my charming, bright <hi>Olivia!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas, Mr. <hi>Wildman,</hi> theſe Tranſports are not my
Due; you know I am honeſt; neither my Husband nor you can make me
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: Therefore urged by your Thouſand Importunities, I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
ſent for you, but 'tis to forbid any more <hi>Billet Douxes,</hi> not one
Love Letter more, as you hope to have all thoſe kindly received which you
ſhall diſpatch to your next Miſtreſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>You amaze me, Madam!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Secondly, no Corrupting Preſents to my Woman; no
at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting her weak Vertue, in hopes to prevail upon her Ladies; for the
firſt moment I ſuſpect it, I ſhall be offended at you, and ſend her
packing, to carry you the News of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>I was afraid I ſhould ſuffer as an Accomplice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Thirdly, no extravagant Civilities to Mr. <hi>Smyrna;</hi>
no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning cold Affronts with fond Careſſes; no carrying him to the 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51767:22"/>Tavern, and paying his Club there, as if that were to be
the Price of his Wife at home; nor vain Hopes of having the Proverb of your
ſide, <hi>That Cuckolds are kind to thoſe who make them ſo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas ſomething indeed, he was always ſo damn'd jealous
of me; had he had but the Title, I wou'd not have queſtioned the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of
the Proverb, his Horns would have blinded him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Doctor</hi> Pulſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, a good Morning to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>My Husband's Phyſician unſent for! What's to be
done?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>I have been at Mr. <hi>Simpler</hi>'s your Apothecary, who
told me Mr. <hi>Smyrna</hi> was taken dangerouſly ill; whereupon I thought it
my Duty to viſit him: But, bleſſed be God, he's in a fine breathing
Sweat: When he has taken what I ſhall preſcribe, I hope he may be
better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed, Dr. <hi>Pulſe,</hi> he has had a very bad
Night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>By his Habit, I ſhould gueſs this Gentleman to be of the
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty. Pray, Sir, if it may be without Offence, what are you call'd? I do
not believe you to be of the Colledge; I never ſaw your Face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to my
knowledge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>My Buſineſs, Sir, is with my Patients, and not to
anſwer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Queſtions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>Cry you mercy, good <hi>Mr. Mountebank;</hi> a Stage, I
ſuppoſe, is your Occupation. Madam, ſince you have employed this Quack,
e'en make uſe of him for good and all. A lawful Conſultation I ſhould not
have refuſed; and ſo much good may do you with your <hi>Merry
Andrew.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Pulſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm glad he's gone. Mr. <hi>Wildman,</hi> you know your
Doom; we muſt part upon't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee, dear <hi>Olivia,</hi> have more good Nature: Do I
deſerve no Reward for all my unwearied Hours of Love? No ſoft
Compaſſion due for all I have ſuffer'd? This is mortifying one beyond any
thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>They ſay Revenge is natural. For your Comfort then, you
have yours upon me, ſince I can't puniſh you, but I muſt ſhare in't my
ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Were that true, <hi>Olivia,</hi> you cou'd not uſe me
thus. That Kindneſs you once flatter'd me with, tho' it were but a Name, has
now loſt that. You tell me, I am to be ſacrific'd to your Vertue— but
I'm afraid 'tis to ſome more happy Lover.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, I have never enjoy'd you. If Love were my Buſineſs,
might I not find it with you? I never heard before, that any thing beſides
Poſſeſſion brought Satiety.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51767:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Did you never ſtay ſo long for your Dinner, that your A
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite was loſt when you came to it? methinks I ſee you reaſoning with
it, then ſurveying me— And crying 'twon't do, it this the Treat I
long'd for?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Your compariſon might hold indeed, if you cou'd prove I
had ſtay'd my Stomach before I came to Dinner: But my Husband<hi>'s</hi> no
ſuch inviting Diſh, and I can aſſure you, too provident, to allow me
much variety.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Smyrna <hi>ſick in his Night-Gown, led
by</hi> Pulſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>He's a meer Quack, and ſo you'l ſay when you ſee him;
if you make uſe of him, he'l certainly be the Death of you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay Doctor <hi>Pulſe,</hi> not unlikely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Heavens defend me, here's my Husband! Lord, Mr.
<hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> you have affrighted me out of my Wits, my very Heart beats in
my Body. Doctor <hi>Pulſe</hi> ſaid, you were all in a Sweat, and I'm
afraid you'l catch your Death, by riſing in the Cold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twill be very well Miſtreſs, if I find your Heart agree
with your Tongue. But what Quack have you brought me here— Nay, face
about Doctor, I don't doubt your Experience, nor Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering by the Rules of
Art— Mercy on us— Ay marry Sir, this is like a Wife
indeed—What, Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi> turned Phyſician! Friend
<hi>Pulſe,</hi> you need never have troubled your head about this
buſineſs, my Wife meant to keep this able Doctor to her ſelf; this
Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans deſign lay in ſupplanting me, not you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Impudence muſt carry me through, 
<stage>aſide.</stage> Doctor, your Patient is
certainly Diſtracted, a meer Frenzy has ſeized him— Feel but his
Pulſe, ay he's fitter for his Bed than any place elſe; I can't commend your
Judgment in ſuffering him to riſe in this deſperate Condition, let's
force him back to his Chamber.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>If I am mad, 'tis horn mad; you'd carry me to my Chamber,
that you might Iye with my Wife in hers— Pray Doctor <hi>Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> be
pleas'd to march, I ſhall be able to wait upon you down, and ſecure the
Doors after you. Be pleas'd to lead the way without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ceremony— I
muſt own 'tis uncivil, but I make bold by your own example, for I fear, you
have bin more ſo than welcome, with a certain Acquaintance of yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis as I ſay, Doctor, retrieve your blunder, or I am
loſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>Never fear it, Madam.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>apart to</hi> Pulſe.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Brother Doctor, won't you aſſiſt me? The Gentlemans
unruly, ſee how he ſtruggles. O Sir, if you did but underſtand your own
good you'd to go Bed, elſe you're a loſt Man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pulſe, Pulſe,</hi> Friend <hi>Pulſe,</hi> I ſay,
will you let me be murder'd by this Rogue, this Villain <hi>Wildman</hi>—
I'm almoſt ſtrangl'd, help, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51767:23"/>help there, I ſay, I
won't be carried from my Wife— Wife— Wife— Where are you?
Pray Sir be ſatisfied, and think me Cuckold enough for the firſt time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>O dear Husband, be perſwaded and go to Bed, you look
ſtrangely wild.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>Ay Maſter, if you did but ſee your ſelf, what an
altered Man your are; bleſs me one wou'd not know you again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks to honeſt Whoring, Mr. <hi>Wildman</hi>— I
always thought Horns wou'd bring a ſtrange Alteration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Lord, what a Frenzy is this, to miſtake a Phyſician
for a Lover— To bed with him, by all means, and let him have ſome
Cooling Tyſans, and refreſhing Juleps to allay the heat of the Diſtemper,
perhaps a little ſleep may reſtore him— Your Hand, Maſter
Doctor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, if you are in the ſame Song too, I muſt be mad
indeed— When a man is to be made a Cuckold, nothing can prevent it—
But pray, let Maſter Doctor with the Whoring Countenance be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>He has never bin well ſince that Rogue of a Fortune-teller
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch'd him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, if that be his caſe, it may be beyond our Art,
Brother; beſt ſend for ſome godly Divine to Pray over him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oliv.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſhall be my Care— God reſtore him, Doctor
<hi>Pulſe. Phoebe,</hi> lend your Hand, he'l ſtruggle: But we muſt
prevail, 'tis for his good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the Devil in you all? I am no more mad than any of
you; only a Cuckold, and a little troubled at that Calamity; no further
Frantick I profeſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pulſe.</speaker>
                     <p>That's enough, of all Conſcience. In, in with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smyr.</speaker>
                     <p>Murder, help, Murder, Murder.</p>
                     <stage>They carry him off ſtrugling.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Re-enter</hi> Wildman.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>I have enough of the ſport, and had much rather ſee
<hi>Olivia</hi> return.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Phoebe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lady Sir, deſires you would pleaſe to be gone;
ſhe's reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſtay by my Maſter for the better quieting of
him— But don't let this diſhearten you, your affairs ſhall go better
than they have done, or I'll loſe my Place, and my Reputation too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I'm at length convinc'd, <hi>Olivias</hi> Virtue
ſhou'd be rather <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51767:24"/>Cheriſhed than Seduced, tho' I ſee
whoſe ever Title we have to it, we can be no more ſure of Love, than Money;
'tis not ours till we have it in Poſſeſſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Lady</hi> Young Loves <hi>Houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <head>SONG <hi>and</hi> MUSICK.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>TO Love and all its Sweets adieu,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>To glittering Hopes, and glowing Fires;</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>To Eyes that Swore ſhe wou'd be true,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And yield</hi> Philander <hi>his
Deſires.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Thoſe Dear, thoſe faithleſs perſur'd
Eyes,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Thoſe Fatal, ſweet deluding things,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>The Shepherd now forgiving Dyes,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And dying, mournfully he Sings.</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Kinder Death, than Cruel ſhe,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Haſte, oh haſte to ſet me free.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Amorous, <hi>who throws down his Hat,
unbuttons his Coat, croſſes his Arms, hangs down his Head, and walks
deſpairingly; then enter Lady</hi> Young Love <hi>and</hi> Marina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>They have given us but a Melancholy Song Daughter upon our
Wedding day. None here but Sir <hi>Amorous!</hi> Lord Sir, what can be the
reaſon of this diſorder? Jeſu forbid, that ſo handſom a young
Gentleman, ſhou'd have as much deſpair in his Heart as Perſon—
<hi>Marina,</hi> go and bid <hi>Isabel</hi> be ſure to mind what I told
her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Madam.</p>
                     <p>Well done Mother, get as large a ſhare of the Sex as you
can, I'll not ſtay to diſpute your Title.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit. Marina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>What don't you know me Sir. <hi>Amorous</hi>— Bleſs
me, what not anſwer me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Too well Madam— I know you as the cauſe of all my
ills, the glorious cauſe of my undoing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord, my mind miſgave me when I heard that mournful
Song.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51767:24"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſs 'twas dull, unfit for Brides, and cou'd
but dead your thoughts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>But Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> what is the real occaſion of
this Sadneſs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me dye, Madam, if your Ladiſhip does not ridicule my
ſufferings. Have you forgot what I told you laſt Night; that and a
thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more lyes heavy on my Heart to day; and unleſs you
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſee me dead, you muſt not marry Mr.
<hi>Wilmore</hi>—</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He a Wretch inſenſible of all your Charms,</l>
                        <l>And who ſeeks his Happineſs in anothers Arms.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>He Lord, he's the Modeſteſt Gentleman; ſo Civil he
never preſt for the leaſt Favour, no not for a Kiſs; and that you'l
ſay's but a ſmall one; but when he cou'd not decently avoid it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir. <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>A Wretch, is it poſſible Madam, that the Tranſports of
a Man, when alone, with ſo fine a Woman — Oh Madam! Were it but
permitted me— But why do I vainly meditate on any thing but Death!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>Death, Heaven forbid: Indeed I am very ſorry, I was not
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with you, before things came to this extremity — But as to
Mr. <hi>Wilmore,</hi> he is ſo baſhful, and ſo modeſt, Lord, you wou'd
not believe any thing elſe in him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>All that a Rival can ſay, will be ſuſpected: But ſay
I clear'd it to you, what then ſhall be my reward?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed I ſhou'd be furiouſly angry to find him ſo cold
only to me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>If your Ladyſhip will let me wait upon you to the Garden,
I'll clear the matter to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SCENE</hi> Changes to the Garden.</head>
                  <stage>Wilmore, Belira, <hi>meets him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>DO you remember, our laſt Diſcourſe
<hi>Belira?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Can I ever forget any thing where you'r concern'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I muſt tell you, I'm reſolved to Marry where I
beſt can like, not for conveniency alone, 'tis ſinful, and you, and I, and
all muſt live to dye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>So godly, one wou'd think your Time were come: You have
forgot ſure, <hi>Marina</hi> is to marry your Father.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Sir</hi> Amorous <hi>and Lady</hi> Young Love
<hi>appear abſconding.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>She never will <hi>Belira,</hi> therefore if you have Loved,
ſhew it in this only proof, I ever ask't, and let me marry her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:51767:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>How dare you think the queſtion, much leſs to ask it? I
only live for you, in hopes of you; and when thoſe hopes are gone, I've done
with life, the heavy load will not be worth the bearing, the very thought has
looſn'd it, and I want pow'r to anſwer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>No Tears <hi>Belira,</hi> we will be always Friends, your
Honour ſhall be ſafe, and you my chiefeſt care.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>What can pay Love, but Love? <hi>Marinas</hi> Arms will make
you cold to mine; nor can I ſtoop, to ſhare your hurt. O yet conſider!
e're it be too late, think on the Wreck, the ruin of your Fortune, the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Tides of Poverty, that ruins all it covers; and laſtly, think on an unhappy
Wretch, whoſe only fault is deſperate Love of you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I've thought on all, and nicely weighed the Senſe; the
conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is this, I Love <hi>Marina,</hi> and rather than not marry her,
wou'd be undone; therefore if you can ſave me 'twill be Noble, and like the
Love you promiſed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>What Generoſity canſt thou hope to find, where only
injuries are given? what ſuffering, tame, deluded Monſter doſt thou think
me? My Wrongs have waked that Rage, which Wonder had be-calm'd, and I am now
prepared to daſh thy hopes, and prove thee Traytor to thy Vows and me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Be wiſe <hi>Belira!</hi> We live not now in thoſe
Romantick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant days, where their firſt Miſtreſs was their laſt.
I lik'd you once, and ſtill eſteem you, but Vows that are made in Love, are
writ in ſand: It's impoſſible to recal a Lovers Heart, when once 'tis
made a Preſent to another; ſhou'd it return, 'twou'd ſooner Love a
third.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou needſt not ſeek for Arguments to kill my Hopes;
thus I blow them from me: Farewel for ever, both to thy Love and them; thou
haſt Lov'd me little, but thou knowſt me leſs: Vengeance is due to thy
miſtake; I only live to wiſh, and hope to ſee it take your Minion: Love
her as long as you are uſed to Love a Woman, and then let want of Wealth and
Liberty purſue you: Be poorly Wretched, and Wretched Poor; and may you hate
the cauſe as bad as I do Curſe for her ſake, the very name of Woman; yet
think on me and ſigh for ſuch a Friend — But may no Friend be found,
till ſcorned at home thou ſeekeſt abroad, ſome Wretched Death
unknown.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Going to Lady</hi> Young Love, <hi>Sir</hi> Amorous
<hi>meets her.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>What have I heard and ſeen <hi>Belira?</hi> Is it
poſſible it ſhou'd be you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                     <p>Villain, haſt thou betray'd me— Madam, I warn you
from that Traytor <hi>Wilmore,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Belira.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr. Wilmore,</hi> I am ſorry I was ſo long your
pretence, Sir <hi>Amorous.</hi> This diſcovery has done me mighty Service,
and I am ſorry I cannot expreſs my Gratitude to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I have too juſtly offended your Ladyſhip, ever to hope
Forgiveneſs: I only beg your Anger may not fall upon <hi>Marina,</hi> ſhe's
an Innocent cauſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51767:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Y. L.</speaker>
                     <p>The Age is quite Debauch'd, Jeſu! who ſhall we truſt
after this? <hi>Belira</hi> naught, and with modeſt <hi>Mr. Wilmore,</hi> I
am in ſuch amaze, I can't recover my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wildman <hi>and</hi> Marina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the matter? I met <hi>Belira</hi> in a mighty rage,
ſhe ran to this Ladies Chamber with a drawn Sword? 'twas lucky I was in the
way, elſe ſhe had murdered her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhan't recover the fright this month! <hi>Mr.
Wildman</hi> has ſaved my life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>He ſhall always command mine for it, but what's become of
her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>When ſhe ſaw her ſelf Defeated, ſhe ſent for a
Chair, and went away in it; I have not yet troubled my ſelf to know
where.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>No 'tis no matter, ſince my Houſe is rid of her. I
ſhall take care who I entertain a good opinion of again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee <hi>Wilmore,</hi> no Chagrin. This was my Plot, I
durſt not truſt thee with it; and therefore adviſed thee to meet her in
the Garden, I knew thy ſoft Nature, wou'd not ſuffer thee, to Expoſe an
ill Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, tho' to make thy ſelf happy in a good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>If you had, 'twou'd never have come to this; my Pity is due
to an unhappy Woman, who had never bin ſuch, if She had not known me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l make <hi>Marina</hi> Jealous,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope not, ſhe wou'd not have me Barbarous:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Ruſtick Good-heart.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Where are ye all? Before <hi>George</hi> the Canonical hour
will be paſt; yonders the other Young Gentlewoman gone away Diſtracted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Ruſtick,</hi> here's a new Scene of Affairs;
<hi>Marina</hi> Swears, She has more mind to be your Daughter, than your Wife;
and that 'tis better to Drink Caudle by a young Fellow, than be oblig'd to make
it for an Old.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Be-gad, I don't believe a word of this: You are not of his
mind Sweet-heart, Mr. <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> is ready to ſpoil your ſport
Sir, and begin ours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Indeed Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> you have convinc'd me of the
reality of your Paſſion, and were it not for the talk of the Town, you
ſhou'd find me, not ſo inſenſible as you imagine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me be nothing Madam, if this unexpected Marriage will
not put them all out of Countenance, and baulk their Spleen; they are prepared
by Mr. <hi>Wilmore</hi>'s concern for your Daughter, to laugh at your
Ladyſhip. No Wedding— Let me expire, if it wou'd not be a good way, to
prevent his refuſal by yours, and before he asks you to make him happy with
<hi>Marina,</hi> to make me ſo in your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:51767:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>'Twere a good Jeſt indeed, I think we muſt not ſpoil
the Conceit—But then, Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> will you be conſtant?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>As your own Charms, which can never admit of a Decay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Indeed, Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> I have Compaſſion upon
your Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and a juſt Reſentment of <hi>Mr. Wilmore</hi>'s
Ingratitude: Therefore, <hi>Sir Amorous</hi>—but Lord! what was I going
to ſay?—Jeſu!— will not you think me quickly won?—But
indeed, my Charity to you is the chief Inducement; therefore to morrow, <hi>Sir
Amorous,</hi> if you pleaſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>To morrow will not prevent Mr. <hi>Wilmore:</hi> Give me
leave to declare my Happineſs, and to hope you will immediately confirm it
within.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Lard, Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> you overcome me every way; I
leave it to your Diſcretion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Before <hi>George,</hi> not I. Good Mr. Son, no coguing nor
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling with me: I love the Lady my ſelf, and have her I will, or
ſome ſhall ſmart for it. My Lady <hi>Young Love,</hi> here's Felony,
Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and Treaſon againſt you; they would cheat me of my Wife, and
you of your Husband.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>That they will hardly be able to do; I have made my Choice,
Sir <hi>Amorous</hi> can tell you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Hey day! Here's fine juggling indeed! Before
<hi>George,</hi> I don't underſtand theſe <hi>London</hi> Contrivances.
Shall I have your Daughter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous,</hi> you rule me. <hi>Marina,</hi> I have
too long, won by <hi>Bellaria</hi>'s Pretences, deny'd you the Affection of a
Mother; but I'll make amends for all, and leave you the Liberty of your
Choice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Nay then, before <hi>George,</hi> 'tis ſtill well
enough— Give me thy Hand, ſweet Miſtris, 'tis a Match, Bedad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I am afraid, Sir, you'll find me good for little, but to
bring the Addition of Jealouſie to the reſt of your Diſtempers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Ruſ.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>That is in plain Engliſh, Madam, that you wou'd make me a
Cuckold—Wou'd you ſo?—Nay, like enough Bedad— Your Eyes
have a plaguy Lear that way—Hey! 
<stage>[calls within there]</stage> Bid
<hi>Ralph</hi> ſaddle the Horſes, and bring my Boots; I'll not ſtay to
ſee the end on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit Sir</hi> Ruſ.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter, let him go; as I take it, he has Sign'd.
<hi>Wilmore,</hi> thou haſt nothing to do now, but to make thy Claim.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I have ſo true a Senſe of my Villany to this Lady, that
I dare not addreſs for Pardon, much more the unvaluable Bleſſing of her
Daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Amorous</hi> has prevail'd for you, Sir. I forgive
you, and have left <hi>Marina</hi> the Liberty of her Choice. But might I
perſwade her, it ſhou'd not be <hi>Belira</hi>'s Lover, he has too many
Faults.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51767:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>I'll take them all upon my ſelf; and if your Ladyſhip
would conſent, I ſhould not think my ſelf unhappy with Mr.
<hi>Wilmore.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twill be generous, like your ſelf, Madam; and ſhew the
Town, the little Concern you have for Mr. <hi>Wilmore.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir <hi>Am.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Let me expire, Madam, if I can ceaſe my Intreaties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. <hi>Y. L.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You command me, Sir <hi>Amorous.</hi> Take her, Mr.
<hi>Wilmore;</hi> and if poſſible, make amends for your Faults to me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>This Goodneſs confounds me more—My whole Life
ſhall be one conſtant Study to deſerve your Generoſity, and
<hi>Marina</hi>'s Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſo? matters are brought to Perfection. I find I am a
Maſter in the Art. But, Begad, Pimping here, I have ruin'd my own Affairs
with <hi>Orinda.</hi> Will ſhe not be at the Wedding?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>She keeps her Bed very ill, and has ſent an Excuſe; but
I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>Belira</hi>'s Abſence will be the beſt Spell to draw her
thence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſhall be my buſineſs, after the Chaplain has done
his: I'll viſit, and perſwade her to come and wiſh you Joy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>I am impatient till you have the occaſion. Sir
<hi>Amorous,</hi> lead the way with your Bride.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>I think Fortune has not one other Trick to diſappoint you
with; but 'tis beſt to take her when ſhe's obliging, for ſuch all People
that are going to be married think her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But Time will ſhew the Cheat, and you ſhall find</l>
                     <l>The Goddeſs is as fickle as ſhe's kind.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51767:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HAles</hi>'s Contemplations in three Parts, the third Part
never before Printed; to which is added his Life, by <hi>Gilbert</hi> Lord
Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Works of that Excellent Practical Phyſitian, Dr.
<hi>Thomas Sydenham;</hi> wherein, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Hiſtory and Cure of Acute
Diſeaſes are Treated of, after a new and Accurate Method, but alſo the
ſhorteſt and ſafeſt way of Curing moſt <hi>Chronical</hi>
Diſeaſes. Tranſlated from the Original Latin; by <hi>John Pechey,</hi> at
the Colledge of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Behns</hi> Novels, are this day Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>All three are Sold by <hi>R. Wellington</hi> at the <hi>Lute</hi>
in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THE Artificial <hi>Clock-maker.</hi> A Treatiſe of Watch, and
Clock-work: Wherein the Art of Calculating Numbers for moſt ſorts of
Movements, is explained to the capacity of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned. Alſo the Hiſtory
of Clock-work, both Ancient and Modern. With other uſeful matters never
before Publiſhed. By <hi>W. D.</hi> M. A. Printed for <hi>James Knapton</hi>
at the <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
